I'm here to tell you about the real search for alien life.
أنا هنا لأخبركم عن البحث الحقيقي عن الحياة الفضائية
Not little green humanoids arriving in shiny UFOs,
لا عن المخلوقات الخضراء الصغيرة التي تصل في أطباق فضائية لامعة
although that would be nice.
وهذا أيضا سيكون لطيفاً
But it's the search for planets orbiting stars far away.
لكنه بحث عن كواكب تدور حول نجوم بعيدة
Every star in our sky is a sun.
كل نجم في سمائنا هو شمس
And if our sun has planets --
وإذا كان لشمسنا كواكب
Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, etc.,
عطارد والزهرة والأرض والمرّيخ, إلخ...
surely those other stars should have planets also,
حتما سيكون لهذه النجوم كواكب أيضاً
and they do.
وهذا صحيح
And in the last two decades,
وفي العقدين الأخيرين
astronomers have found thousands of exoplanets.
وقد وجد علماء الفلك الآلاف من الكواكب الخارجية
Our night sky is literally teeming with exoplanets.
فعلاً سماؤنا تعج ليلا بالكواكب الخارجية
We know, statistically speaking,
ونحن نعلم، من الناحية الاحصائية
that every star has at least one planet.
أن كل نجم له على الأقل كوكب واحد
And in the search for planets,
وعند البحث عن كواكب
and in the future, planets that might be like Earth,
في المستقبل الكواكب التي ستكون مثل الأرض
we're able to help address
سنكون قادرين على طرح
some of the most amazing and mysterious questions
بعض الأسئلة الأكثر غرابة وغموضاً
that have faced humankind for centuries.
التي واجهت الإنسان منذ قرون
Why are we here?
لماذا نحن هنا؟
Why does our universe exist?
لماذا يوجد هذا الكون؟
How did Earth form and evolve?
كيف تكونت الأرض وتطورت؟
How and why did life originate and populate our planet?
كيف ولماذا نشأت الحياة وعمّرت كوكبنا؟
The second question that we often think about is:
السؤال الثاني الذي غالبا ما نفكّر فيه:
Are we alone?
هل نحن وحدنا؟
Is there life out there?
هل توجد هناك حياة؟
Who is out there?
من هناك؟
You know, this question has been around for thousands of years,
كما تعلمون, هذا السؤال يحيط بنا منذ آلاف السنين
since at least the time of the Greek philosophers.
منذ زمن الفلاسفة الإغريق على الأقلّ
But I'm here to tell you just how close we're getting
ولكن أنا هنا لأخبركم فقط, كم اقتربنا
to finding out the answer to this question.
من الإجابة على هذا السؤال
It's the first time in human history that this really is within reach for us.
إنها أول مرة في تاريخ الإنسان حيث أن هذا حقا في متناولنا
Now when I think about the possibilities for life out there,
الآن, حينما أفكر في احتمالات وجود الحياه هناك
I think of the fact that our sun is but one of many stars.
أفكر في حقيقة أن شمسنا ليست إلا واحدة من الكثير من النجوم
This is a photograph of a real galaxy,
هذه صورة حقيقية لمجرة
we think our Milky Way looks like this galaxy.
نحن نعتقد أن مجرة درب التبانة مثل هذه المجرة
It's a collection of bound stars.
إنها مجموعة من النجوم المترابطة
But our [sun] is one of hundreds of billions of stars
لكن شمسنا هي واحدة من مئات مليارات النجوم
and our galaxy is one of upwards of hundreds of billions of galaxies.
ومجرتنا هي واحدة من أكثر من مئات مليارات المجرات
Knowing that small planets are very common,
مع العلم أن هذه الكواكب الصغيرة متشابهة جدا
you can just do the math.
بقدر بسيط من الرياضيات
And there are just so many stars and so many planets out there,
وهناك الكثير من النجوم والكثير من الكواكب هناك،
that surely, there must be life somewhere out there.
فمن المؤكد أن تكون هناك حياة في مكان ما هناك.
Well, the biologists get furious with me for saying that,
حسنا، فإن علماء الأحياء سيغضبون مني لقول ذلك،
because we have absolutely no evidence for life beyond Earth yet.
لأنه ليس لدينا على الإطلاق أي دليل على الحياة خارج الأرض حتى الآن.
Well, if we were able to look at our galaxy from the outside
حسنا, إذا كنا قادرين على رؤية مجرتنا من الخارج
and zoom in to where our sun is,
ثم تكبيرالمشهد نحو شمسنا
we see a real map of the stars.
سنرى خريطة حقيقية للنجوم
And the highlighted stars are those with known exoplanets.
والنجوم البارزة هي تلك التي لها كواكب خارجية معروفة
This is really just the tip of the iceberg.
إنها فقط الجزء البارز من الجبل الجليدي
Here, this animation is zooming in onto our solar system.
هنا, في هذا العرض نكبر نحو النظام الشمسي
And you'll see here the planets
وهنا سترى الكواكب
as well as some spacecraft that are also orbiting our sun.
وكذلك بعض المركبات الفضائية التي تدور أيضا حول شمسنا
Now if we can imagine going to the West Coast of North America,
الآن, إذا تخيلنا التوجه إلى الساحل الغربي لأمريكا الشمالية
and looking out at the night sky,
والنظر عبر السماء ليلاً
here's what we'd see on a spring night.
هذا ما سنراه في ليلة من فصل الربيع
And you can see the constellations overlaid
ويمكنك أن ترى المجموعات النجمية تزينها
and again, so many stars with planets.
ثم العديد من النجوم مع كواكبها
There's a special patch of the sky where we have thousands of planets.
هناك بقعة مميزة فى السماء حيث نجد الآلاف من الكواكب
This is where the Kepler Space Telescope focused for many years.
هنا حيث يركز تلسكوب كبلر الفضائي منذ سنوات
Let's zoom in and look at one of the favorite exoplanets.
لنكبّر وننظر إلى أحد الكواكب الخارجية المفضلة
This star is called Kepler-186f.
هذا النجم يسمى كبلر-186ف
It's a system of about five planets.
إنه نظام بحوالي خمسة كواكب
And by the way, most of these exoplanets, we don't know too much about.
بالمناسبة, أغلب هذه الكواكب الخارجية لا نعرف عنها الكثير
We know their size, and their orbit and things like that.
نعرف حجمها ومدارها وأشياء من هذا القبيل
But there's a very special planet here called Kepler-186f.
لكن هناك كوكب مميز اسمه كبلر- 186ف
This planet is in a zone that is not too far from the star,
الكوكب يوجد داخل منطقة لا تبعد كثيرا عن النجم
so that the temperature may be just right for life.
لهذا فالحرارة قد تكون مناسبة للحياة
Here, the artist's conception is just zooming in
هنا, في نموذج المحاكاة نقرّب
and showing you what that planet might be like.
ونظهر لكم كيف سيبدو هذا الكوكب
So, many people have this romantic notion of astronomers
لهذا, كثير من الناس لديهم هذه الفكرة الرومانسية عن الفلكيين
going to the telescope on a lonely mountaintop
الذهاب إلى مرصد فلكي وحيدا على قمة جبل
and looking at the spectacular night sky through a big telescope.
والنظر إلى السماء المذهلة ليلا عبر تلسكوب
But actually, we just work on our computers like everyone else,
لكن حاليا, نحن نعمل فقط على حواسيبنا كأي شخص آخر
and we get our data by email or downloading from a database.
ونحصل على معلوماتنا عبر البريد الإلكتروني أو التحميل من قاعدة البيانات
So instead of coming here to tell you
وبدَلَ أن القدوم إلى هنا لأخبركم
about the somewhat tedious nature of the data and data analysis
عن الطبيعة المملة نوعاً ما للبيانات وتحليلها
and the complex computer models we make,
ونماذج الحاسوب المعقدة التي نقوم بها
I have a different way to try to explain to you
لدي طريقة مختلفة أفسر لكم بها
some of the things that we're thinking about exoplanets.
بعض الأمور التي نعتقدها عن الكواكب الخارجية
Here's a travel poster:
وهنا ملصق السفر
"Kepler-186f:
"كبلر-186 ف
Where the grass is always redder on the other side."
حيث العشب هو دائما أكثر احمرارا على الجانب الآخر
That's because Kepler-186f orbits a red star,
لأن كبلر-186 ف يدور حول نجم أحمر
and we're just speculating that perhaps the plants there,
ونحن فقط نفترض أنه ربما تكون نباتات هناك
if there is vegetation that does photosynthesis,
إذا كانت هناك نباتات تقوم بالنركيب الضوئي
it has different pigments and looks red.
ستكون لديها أصباغ مختلفة وتبدو حمراء
"Enjoy the gravity on HD 40307g,
"تمتع بالجاذبية على إتش دي 40307 جي
a Super-Earth."
الأرض الكبرى أو (السوبر)
This planet is more massive than Earth
هذا الكوكب أثقل من الأرض
and has a higher surface gravity.
وله جاذبية أكبر
"Relax on Kepler-16b,
"استرخِ على كبلر-16ب
where your shadow always has company."
حيث تكون لظلك دائمة رفقة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We know of a dozen planets that orbit two stars,
نعلم عن اثني عشر كوكبا تدور حول نجمين
and there's likely many more out there.
وربما هناك أكثر من ذلك
If we could visit one of those planets,
إذا كان بإمكاننا زيارة أحد هذه الكواكب
you literally would see two sunsets
كنت سترى غروبين للشمس
and have two shadows.
وسيكون لك ظِلاّن
So actually, science fiction got some things right.
وحاليا, قدّم الخيال العلمي بعض الأمور الصحيحة
Tatooine from Star Wars.
تاتوين من حرب النجوم
And I have a couple of other favorite exoplanets
ولدي زوج من الكواكب الخارجية الأخرى
to tell you about.
لأخبركم عنها
This one is Kepler-10b,
هذا هو كبلر-10ب
it's a hot, hot planet.
إنه حارّ, كوكب ساخن
It orbits over 50 times closer to its star
إنه يدور أكثر من خمسين مرة أقرب إلى شمسه
than our Earth does to our sun.
مقارنة بأرضنا مع شمسنا
And actually, it's so hot,
وهو حاليا, حارٌّ جدّاً
we can't visit any of these planets, but if we could,
لا يمكننا زيارة أي من هذه الكواكب, ولكن إن أمكننا
we would melt long before we got there.
سنذوب قبل الوصول هناك
We think the surface is hot enough to melt rock
نعتقد أن سطحه حارّ بشكل كافٍ لذوبان الصخور
and has liquid lava lakes.
وفيه بحيرات حمم سائلة
Gliese 1214b.
كَليز 1214 ب
This planet, we know the mass and the size
هذا الكوكب نعرف كثلته وحجمه
and it has a fairly low density.
وله كثافة منخفضة نسبياً
It's somewhat warm.
أنه حارّ نوعا ما
We actually don't know really anything about this planet,
ونحن لا نعلم حاليا أي شيء عن هذا الكوكب
but one possibility is that it's a water world,
ولكن إمكانية واحدة هي أنه عالم من المياه
like a scaled-up version of one of Jupiter's icy moons
وكأنه نسخة مصغرة لأحد الأقمار الجليدية المشتري
that might be 50 percent water by mass.
قد يشكل الماء نصف كثلته
And in this case, it would have a thick steam atmosphere
وفي هذه الحالة, ستكون في جوّه طبقة سميكة من البخار
overlaying an ocean,
بدلاً من تواجد المحيط المعروف لدينا
not of liquid water,
ليس بالماء السائل
but of an exotic form of water, a superfluid --
ولكن في حالة غريبة, فائق الميوعة
not quite a gas, not quite a liquid.
ليس قريبا من الغاز وليس قريبا من السائل
And under that wouldn't be rock,
ولن تكون تحته صخور
but a form of high-pressure ice,
بل شكل من الجليد تحت ضغط شديد
like ice IX.
مثل "جليد 9"
So out of all these planets out there,
إذن من بين جميع هذه الكواكب الموجودة
and the variety is just simply astonishing,
والتنوع ببساطة مذهل
we mostly want to find the planets that are Goldilocks planets, we call them.
أغلبنا يريد إيجاد كواكب نسمّيها كواكب معتدلة
Not too big, not too small,
ليست كبيرة جدا ولا صغيرة جدا
not too hot, not too cold --
ولا ساخنة جدا ولا باردة جدا
but just right for life.
ولكنها مناسبة لتواجد حياة عليها.
But to do that, we'd have to be able to look
ولهذا, كان يجب أن نكون قادرين على إختبار
at the planet's atmosphere,
الغلاف الجوي هذا الكوكب
because the atmosphere acts like a blanket trapping heat --
لكن الجو يتصرف كغطاء يحتفظ بالحرارة
the greenhouse effect.
أو ما يعرف بالاحتباس الحراري
We have to be able to assess the greenhouse gases
يجب أن نكون قادرين على تقييم الغازات المسببة للاحتباس
on other planets.
في الكواكب الأخرى
Well, science fiction got some things wrong.
حسنا, الخيال العلمي أخطأ في بعض الأمور
The Star Trek Enterprise
المركبة "Enterprise" في مسلسل ستار تراك
had to travel vast distances at incredible speeds
كان عليها أن تقطع مسافات بسرعات خارقة
to orbit other planets
لتدور حول كواكب أخرى
so that First Officer Spock could analyze the atmosphere
لكي يستطيع الضابط الأول سبوك تحليل الجو
to see if the planet was habitable
ليرى إذا كان الكوكب قابلا للسكن
or if there were lifeforms there.
أو إذا كانت نوجد أشكال للحياة هناك.
Well, we don't need to travel at warp speeds
حسنا, لن نحتاج للسفر بسرعة الضوء
to see other planet atmospheres,
لرؤية أجواء الكواكب
although I don't want to dissuade any budding engineers
غير أني لا أريد ثني المهندسين الناشئين
from figuring out how to do that.
عن معرفة كيفية القيام بذلك
We actually can and do study planet atmospheres
يمكننا حاليا القيام بدراسة أجواء الكوكب
from here, from Earth orbit.
من هنا، من مدار الأرض.
This is a picture, a photograph of the Hubble Space Telescope
هذه صورة، صورة لتلسكوب الفضاء هابل
taken by the shuttle Atlantis as it was departing
بواسطة المكوك اتلانتيس عندما كان مغادراً
after the last human space flight to Hubble.
بعد رحلات الفضاء البشرية الأخيرة لهابل
They installed a new camera, actually,
قاموا بتثبيت كاميرا جديدة
that we use for exoplanet atmospheres.
وهي التي نستخدمها حاليا لأجواء كواكب
And so far, we've been able to study dozens of exoplanet atmospheres,
وحتى الآن، كنا قادرين على دراسة العشرات من الأغلفة الجوية لكواكب خارجية
about six of them in great detail.
حوالي ستة منهم بقدر كبير من التفصيل
But those are not small planets like Earth.
لكنها لم تكن كواكب صغيرة مثل الأرض
They're big, hot planets that are easy to see.
إنها كواكب كبيرة وساخنة و من السهل رؤيتها
We're not ready,
لسنا مستعدين
we don't have the right technology yet to study small exoplanets.
ليست لدينا بعد التكنولوجيا الملائمة لدراسة الكواكب الخارجية الصغيرة
But nevertheless,
ومع ذلك
I wanted to try to explain to you how we study exoplanet atmospheres.
حاولت أن أشرح لكم كيف ندرس أجواء كوكب خارج المجموعة الشمسية
I want you to imagine, for a moment, a rainbow.
أريدك أن تتخيلوا، للحظة، قوس قزح
And if we could look at this rainbow closely,
إذا استطعنا أن ننظر في قوس قزح بشكل أقرب
we would see that some dark lines are missing.
سوف نرى أن بعض الخطوط الداكنة مفقودة
And here's our sun,
وهذه أشعة شمسنا
the white light of our sun split up,
الضوء الأبيض من شمسنا ينقسم
not by raindrops, but by a spectrograph.
ليس بسبب قطرات المطر، ولكن بواسطة مطياف
And you can see all these dark, vertical lines.
ويمكنكم أت تروا كل هذه الخطوط العمودية المظلمة
Some are very narrow, some are wide,
بعضها رفيعة جدا، وبعضها عريض
some are shaded at the edges.
بعضها مظلل عند الحواف
And this is actually how astronomers have studied objects in the heavens,
حاليا هذه هي الطريقة التي درس بها علماء الفلك الأجرام السماوية
literally, for over a century.
فعلياً, لأكثر من قرن
So here, each different atom and molecule
وهنا، كل ذرة مختلفة وجزيئة
has a special set of lines,
لها طريقة ترتيب مميزة من الخطوط
a fingerprint, if you will.
بصمة, إذا صح التعبير
And that's how we study exoplanet atmospheres.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي ندرس أجواء كواكب خارجية
And I'll just never forget when I started working
لن أنسى أبدا عندما بدأت العمل
on exoplanet atmospheres 20 years ago,
على أجواء كواكب خارجية قبل 20 عاما
how many people told me,
قال لي كثير من الناس
"This will never happen.
"هذا لن يحدث أبدا
We'll never be able to study them. Why are you bothering?"
لن تقدري أبدا على دراستها لماذا تكلفين نفسك العناء؟"
And that's why I'm pleased to tell you about all the atmospheres studied now,
ولهذا السبب أنا سعيدة لأطلعكم على كل دراسات الأجواء الآن
and this is really a field of its own.
وهذ حقا حقل في حد ذاته
So when it comes to other planets, other Earths,
وعندما يتعلق الأمر بالكواكب الأخرى، أرض أخرى
in the future when we can observe them,
في المستقبل عندما نستطيع أن نراها
what kind of gases would we be looking for?
أي نوع من الغازات سنبحث عنه؟
Well, you know, our own Earth has oxygen in the atmosphere
حسنا، كما تعلمون، على أرضنا يوجد الأكسجين في الغلاف الجوي
to 20 percent by volume.
بنسبة 20 في المئة من الحجم
That's a lot of oxygen.
وهذا كثير من الأوكسجين
But without plants and photosynthetic life,
ولكن دون نباتات وأحياء تقوم بالتركيب الضوئي
there would be no oxygen,
لن يكون هناك أكسجين
virtually no oxygen in our atmosphere.
فعليا, لا أكسجين في الغلاف الجوي
So oxygen is here because of life.
إذن الأكسجين هنا بفضل الحياة
And our goal then is to look for gases in other planet atmospheres,
وهدفنا بالتالي هو البجث عن الغازات في أجواء الكواكب الأخرى
gases that don't belong,
الغازات التي لا تنتمي إليها
that we might be able to attribute to life.
والتي يمكن لنا من خلال تواجدها أن نتوقع وجود حياة.
But which molecules should we search for?
لكن أي الجزيئات يجب أن نبحث عنها؟
I actually told you how diverse exoplanets are.
وقد أخبرتكم كم هي متنوعة تلك الكواكب الخارجية
We expect that to continue in the future
نتوقع أن يستمر هذا في المستقبل
when we find other Earths.
عندما نجد أرضٍ أخرى.
And that's one of the main things I'm working on now,
وهذه واحدة من أهم الأشياء التي أعمل عليها الآن
I have a theory about this.
لي نظرية حول هذا الموضوع
It reminds me that nearly every day,
تذكرني بأن كل يوم تقريبا
I receive an email or emails
أتلقى رسالة أو رسائل بريد إلكتروني
from someone with a crazy theory about physics of gravity
من شخص ما مع نظرية مجنونة حول فيزياء الجاذبية
or cosmology or some such.
أو علم الكونيات أو شيء من هذا القبيل
So, please don't email me one of your crazy theories.
لهذا لا تراسلني عبر البريد الإلكتروني بواحدة من نظرياتك المجنونة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, I had my own crazy theory.
حسنا, أنا أيضا كانت لي نظريتي المجنونة
But, who does the MIT professor go to?
ولكن ما الذي ذهب إليه أستاذ MIT
Well, I emailed a Nobel Laureate in Physiology or Medicine
حسنا لقد أرسلت بالبريد الإلكتروني إلى الفائز بجائزة نوبل في الفسيولوجيا أو الطب
and he said, "Sure, come and talk to me."
فقال لي: "بالطبع, تعالي وتحدثي إلي"
So I brought my two biochemistry friends
ثم أحضرت صديقين لي في الكيمياء الحيوية
and we went to talk to him about our crazy theory.
وذهبنا للتحدث معه حول نظريتنا المجنونة
And that theory was that life produces all small molecules,
وهذه النظرية هي أن الحياة تنتج كل الجزيئات الصغيرة
so many molecules.
وكذا العديد من الجزيئات
Like, everything I could think of, but not being a chemist.
مثل كل شيء فكرت فيه، ماعدا أن أكون متخصصة كيمياء
Think about it:
فكروا في هذا
carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide,
ثاني أكسيد الكربون، أول أكسيد الكربون
molecular hydrogen, molecular nitrogen,
الهيدروجين الجزيئي والنيتروجين الجزيئي
methane, methyl chloride --
الميثان، وكلوريد الميثيل
so many gases.
وكذا العديد من الغازات
They also exist for other reasons,
وهي توجد أيضا لأسباب أخرى
but just life even produces ozone.
لكن الحياة تنتج حتى الأوزون
So we go to talk to him about this,
هكذا ذهبنا للتحدث معه حول هذا الموضوع
and immediately, he shot down the theory.
وعلى الفور، أسقط النظرية
He found an example that didn't exist.
وجد مثالا لم يكن موجودا
So, we went back to the drawing board
ثم عدنا إلى لوحة الرسم
and we think we have found something very interesting in another field.
ونعتقد أننا قد وجدنا شيئا مثيرا جدا للاهتمام في مجال آخر
But back to exoplanets,
لكن لنعد إلى الكواكب الخارجية
the point is that life produces so many different types of gases,
المسألة هي أن الحياة تنتج العديد من أنواع مختلفة من الغازات
literally thousands of gases.
بل الآلاف من الغازات
And so what we're doing now is just trying to figure out
وما نقوم به الآن هو مجرد محاولة لمعرفة
on which types of exoplanets,
على أي نوع من الكواكب الخارجية
which gases could be attributed to life.
أي الغازات يمكن نسبتها الحياة.
And so when it comes time when we find gases
و حتى حينما نجد الغازات
in exoplanet atmospheres
في أجواء كواكب خارجية
that we won't know if they're being produced
لن يمكننا معرفة إن كانت قد انتجت
by intelligent aliens or by trees,
من طرف مخلوق فضائي ذكي أو أشجار
or a swamp,
أو مستنقع
or even just by simple, single-celled microbial life.
أو فقط عن طريق حياة مكروبية بسيطة وحيدة الخلية
So working on the models
إذن العمل على نماذج
and thinking about biochemistry,
والتفكير في الكيمياء الحيوية
it's all well and good.
كل هذا شيء حسن وجيد
But a really big challenge ahead of us is: how?
لكن تحديا كبيرا حقيقيا أمامنا هو: كيف؟
How are we going to find these planets?
كيف سنعثر على هذه الكواكب؟
There are actually many ways to find planets,
حاليا, هناك طرق متعددة لإيجاد الكواكب
several different ways.
طرق مختلفة كثيرة
But the one that I'm most focused on is how can we open a gateway
والتي أركز عليها كثيرا هو كيف يمكننا فتح بوابة
so that in the future,
وهذا في المستقبل
we can find hundreds of Earths.
سنقدر أن نجد مئات من كواكب الأرض
We have a real shot at finding signs of life.
لدينا لقطة حقيقية في العثور على علامات للحياة
And actually, I just finished leading a two-year project
وفي الواقع، لقد انتهيت للتو من قيادة المشروع لمدة عامين
in this very special phase
في هذه المرحلة الخاصة جدا
of a concept we call the starshade.
لمفهوم ندعوه "ظل النجم"
And the starshade is a very specially shaped screen
وظل النجم هو حاجز مشكل بطريقة مميزة جدا
and the goal is to fly that starshade
والهدف أن يطير ظل النجم هذا
so it blocks out the light of a star
بحيث يحجب ضوء نجم ما
so that the telescope can see the planets directly.
وهكذا يستطيع التلسكوب رؤية الكواكب مباشرة
Here, you can see myself and two team members
هنا, يمكنكم رؤيتي مع عضوين من الفريق
holding up one small part of the starshade.
نمسك جزءا صغيرا من ظل النجم.
It's shaped like a giant flower,
شكله كزهرة كبيرة
and this is one of the prototype petals.
وهذه واحدة من نماذج البتلات
The concept is that a starshade and telescope could launch together,
والمبدأ هو أنه يمكن إطلاق ظل النجم والتلسكوب معا
with the petals unfurling from the stowed position.
مع تمدد البتلات من الموضع المخفي
The central truss would expand,
الحزمة المركزية ستتوسع
with the petals snapping into place.
ثم تأخذ البتلات أماكنها
Now, this has to be made very precisely,
الآن, يجب أن يصنع هذا بدقة متناهية
literally, the petals to microns
حرفيا, البتلات بالميكرومتر
and they have to deploy to millimeters.
ثم يتوسع إلى ملمترات
And this whole structure would have to fly
وهذا البنية العملاقة يجب أن تطير
tens of thousands of kilometers away from the telescope.
عشرات آلاف الكيلومترات بعيدا عن التلسكوب
It's about tens of meters in diameter.
وقطرها يناهز عشرات الأمتار
And the goal is to block out the starlight to incredible precision
ودورها هو حجب ضوء النجم بدقة متناهية
so that we'd be able to see the planets directly.
وهكذا سنستطيع رؤية الكواكب مباشرة
And it has to be a very special shape,
ويجب أن تكون بشكل مميز جدا
because of the physics of defraction.
بسبب فيزياء الحيود
Now this is a real project that we worked on,
وهذا مشروع حقيقي نعمل عليه
literally, you would not believe how hard.
في الحقيقة, لا يمكنكم تصور صعوبة الأمر
Just so you believe it's not just in movie format,
أنتم فقط تعتقدون أنها ليست على شاكلة الأفلام
here's a real photograph
هذه صورة حقيقية
of a second-generation starshade deployment test bed in the lab.
للجيل الثاني من ظل النجم في نشر تجريبي في المختبر
And in this case, I just wanted you to know
وفي هذه الحالة أريدكم فقط أن تعلموا
that that central truss has heritage left over
أن هذه الحزمة المركزية ستترك إرثا خلفها
from large radio deployables in space.
من موجات الراديو المنتشرة في الفضاء
So after all of that hard work
وهكذا بعد كل هذا العمل الشاق
where we try to think of all the crazy gases that might be out there,
حينما نحاول التفكير في كل الغازات المجنونة التي يمكن ان تكون هناك
and we build the very complicated space telescopes
ونبني التلسكوب الفضائي الأكثر تعقيدا
that might be out there,
الذي يمكن أن يكون هناك
what are we going to find?
ما الذي سنجده؟
Well, in the best case,
حسنا, في أفضل الأحوال
we will find an image of another exo-Earth.
سنجد صورة لأرض أخرى خارج النظام الشمسي
Here is Earth as a pale blue dot.
هذه هي الأرض نقطة زرقاء شاحبة
And this is actually a real photograph of Earth
وهذه بالفعل صورة حقيقية للأرض
taken by the Voyager 1 spacecraft,
أخذت من طرف المركبة الفضائية "فوياجر 1"
four billion miles away.
عن بعد 4 مليارات ميل
And that red light is just scattered light in the camera optics.
وهذا الضوء الأحمر هو مجرد ضوء مبعثر في بصريات الكاميرا
But what's so awesome to consider
لكن الأكثر روعة هو اعتبار
is that if there are intelligent aliens
أنه إذا كان هناك فضائيون أذكياء
orbiting on a planet around a star near to us
يدورون داخل كوكب حول نجم قريب منا
and they build complicated space telescopes
وصنعوا تلسكوبا فضائيا متطورا
of the kind that we're trying to build,
مثل هذا التلسكوب الذي نحن في طور بنائه
all they'll see is this pale blue dot,
كلما سيرونه هو تلك النقطة الزرقاء الشاحبة
a pinprick of light.
بصيص من الضوء
And so sometimes, when I pause to think
وحتى في بعض الأحيان، عندما أتوقف للتفكير
about my professional struggle and huge ambition,
في كفاحي المهني وطموحي الهائل
it's hard to think about that
من الصعب التفكير في هذا
in contrast to the vastness of the universe.
مقارنة بالحجم الهائل للكون
But nonetheless, I am devoting the rest of my life
ورغم ذلك، سأكرس بقية حياتي
to finding another Earth.
لإيجاد أرض أخرى
And I can guarantee
وأستطيع أن أضمن
that in the next generation of space telescopes,
أنه في الجيل التالي من التلسكوبات الفضائية
in the second generation,
والجيل الثاني
we will have the capability to find and identity other Earths.
ستكون لدينا القدرة على إيجاد وتعريف كواكب أرض أخرى
And the capability to split up the starlight
والقدرة على تحليل ضوء النجوم
so that we can look for gases
وهكذا نستطيع رؤية الغازات
and assess the greenhouse gases in the atmosphere,
والتأكد من غازات الدفيئة في الغلاف الجوي
estimate the surface temperature,
وتقدير حرارة السطح
and look for signs of life.
ورؤية إشارات لوجود الحياة
But there's more.
ولكن هناك المزيد
In this case of searching for other planets like Earth,
وهي هذه الحالة البحث عن كواكب شبيهة للأرض
we are making a new kind of map
نحن نضع نوعا جديدا من الخرائط
of the nearby stars and of the planets orbiting them,
للنجوم القريبة والكواكب التي تدور حولها
including [planets] that actually might be inhabitable by humans.
بما في ذلك النجوم التي قد تكون غير قابلة حاليا للعيش من قبل البشر.
And so I envision that our descendants,
وهكذا أتصور أن ذريتنا
hundreds of years from now,
بعد مئات السنين
will embark on an interstellar journey to other worlds.
ستقوم برحلات بين النجوم نحو عوالم أخرى
And they will look back at all of us
وسوف ينظرون للوراء إلي كل واحد منا
as the generation who first found the Earth-like worlds.
على أننا الجيل الذي وجد الكواكب المشابهة للأرض.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
June Cohen: And I give you, for a question,
جون كوهين: وسأعطيك الفرصة لطرح سؤال
Rosetta Mission Manager Fred Jansen.
مدير بعثة روزيتا فريد يانسن
Fred Jansen: You mentioned halfway through
فريد يانسن: ذكرتِ في منتصف الطريق أن
that the technology to actually look at the spectrum
التكنولوجيا إلى الأن لم تحصل بعدُ على صورة طيف
of an exoplanet like Earth is not there yet.
لكوكب خارجي يشبه الأرض
When do you expect this will be there,
متى تتوقعون أن هذا سيكون
and what's needed?
وما هو المطلوب؟
Actually, what we expect is what we call our next-generation Hubble telescope.
في الواقع، ما نتوقعه هو ما نسميه الجيل المقبل من تلسكوب هابل
And this is called the James Webb Space Telescope,
وأطلقنا عليه اسم تلسكوب الفضاء "جيمس ويب"
and that will launch in 2018,
وسيتم إطلاقه في 2018
and that's what we're going to do,
وهذا ما سنفعله
we're going to look at a special kind of planet
سنوجهه نجو نوع مميز من الكواكب
called transient exoplanets,
يسمى الكواكب الخارجية العابرة
and that will be our first shot at studying small planets
والتي ستكون أول صورة لنا في دراسة الكواكب الصغيرة
for gases that might indicate the planet is habitable.
للغازات التي قد تدل على أن الكوكب صالح للسكن
as the generalist.
كمتتبعة عام
So I am really struck by the notion in your career
لذلك أنا مندهشة حقا من فكرة في حياتك المهنية
of the opposition you faced,
والمعارضة التي واجهتها
that when you began thinking about exoplanets,
عندما بدأت التفكير في الكواكب الخارجية
there was extreme skepticism in the scientific community
هناك تشكيك مبالغ فيه داخل المجتمع العلمي أنها موجودة
that they existed,
وأنت أثبتِ خطأهم
What did it take to take that on?
ما الذي دفعك لفعل هذا الأمر؟
SS: Well, the thing is that as scientists,
سارة سيڭر: حسنا, الأمر هو أننا كعلماء
we're supposed to be skeptical,
نحن من المفترض أن تكون متشككين
because our job to make sure that what the other person is saying
لأن واجبنا أن نتأكد من أن ما يقوله الشخص الآخر
actually makes sense or not.
فعلا, منطقي أو لا.
But being a scientist,
لكن أن تكون عالما
I think you've seen it from this session,
أعتقد أنك قد رأيت ذلك من هذه الندوة
it's like being an explorer.
إنها مثل أن تكون مستكشفا
You have this immense curiosity,
لديك هذا الفضول الهائل
this stubbornness,
هذا العناد
this sort of resolute will that you will go forward
هذا النوع من الإرادة الحازمة التي ستدفعك إلى الأمام
no matter what other people say.
بغضّ النظر عن ما يقوله الآخرون
JC: I love that. Thank you, Sara.
جون كوهين: أحب ذلك. شكرا لك يا سارة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)